<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-21T14:07:22-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">David Sasson</title><subtitle>A blog about technology and health related stuff</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why Data Science is Hard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Data Science is Hard" /><published>2018-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hard/">&lt;p&gt;After a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dsasson48/dataviz/&quot;&gt;data visualization workshop&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nus-datathon.com/&quot;&gt;NUS datathon&lt;/a&gt; someone came up to me and asked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I couldn’t learn any of this stuff from online tutorials—how do you make it seem so easy?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two semesters in the deep end of data science after my biochemistry degree, I’ve echoed her sentiment from time to time. I wrote this blog post to say one thing: data science is difficult. Don’t let others tell you otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this isn’t necessarily a fresh take or earth shattering news, I think it’s important to reiterate for beginners and veterans alike. It’s intimidating to hear people use Tensorflow vocabulary, but I can guarantee you none of those people knew what linear regression was from day one. Regardless of your SAT score, previous job, or experience with a computer—if you put in the work and are genuinely curious this field can get you far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think machine learning has a steep learning curve full of confusing terms to keep interested learners away and data scientists expensive, scarce, and employed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*x7P7gqjo8k2_bj2rTQWAfg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m also here to say that it’s worth it: any discipline, problem, or person could benefit from your skills. The data science tool belt equips you with the most state of the art weapon of mass destruction for change. The beauty of this whole process is that you’re obligated to choose how you want to make that change. From finance to forecasting, retail to robots, and most things in between: machine learning is clearly here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next time you’re struggling through an R package or trying to understand what the fuck a perceptron actually is, make sure to take a step back and realize that you’re surfing a huge, interdisciplinary, accelerating tsunami of information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="learning" /><category term="data science" /><category term="advice" /><summary type="html">After a data visualization workshop at the NUS datathon someone came up to me and asked:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Cross Register</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/evals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Cross Register" /><published>2018-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/evals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/evals/">&lt;p&gt;Deciding what to learning can seem daunting at times. With tons of interesting courses and life-changing professors, how does one choose which classes to take? I decided to investigate this quesiton using my school’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/office-of-education/course-evaluations/&quot;&gt;course evaluations&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&quot;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tidytextmining.com/&quot;&gt;tidytext&lt;/a&gt;. Code is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/dsasson48/evals&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each course evaluation has three quesitons regarding teaching quality with scores from 1-5 corresponding to agreeability. There is also a free text section for comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the three questions are all highly correlated. Not too suprising that highly rated courses have good teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/corr.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like 2016 had more respondents than the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/yr.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And schools have different popularity over years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/schools.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as each school’s overall rating&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/rating.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make sense of the comments, each word is assigned a score from -5 to +5 corresponding to the overall sentiment expressed, as seen in this cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/words.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the word frequency in certain classes
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/freq.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can average the sentiment from school specific comments and compare
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sent_school.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this plot shows the distribtution of word scores for each school
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dist.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;psa&quot;&gt;PSA&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering: yes, I am that much of a nerd.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="learning" /><category term="data viz" /><category term="sentiment analysis" /><summary type="html">Deciding what to learning can seem daunting at times. With tons of interesting courses and life-changing professors, how does one choose which classes to take? I decided to investigate this quesiton using my school’s course evaluations, ggplot2, and tidytext. Code is available here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three thoughts on Dr. Google</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/goog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three thoughts on Dr. Google" /><published>2018-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/goog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/goog/">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month Verily came out with an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/fTtQCu&quot;&gt;piece of software&lt;/a&gt; that identifies several covariates with surprising accuracy from retinal scans of 300,000 patients. These features are fed into a model which yields the probability of suffering a major cardiac event. Although we’ve seen several versions of medical algorithms that aim to supplement or (gasp) replace physicians, this tech is unique in that it’s trying to repurpose existing data. Furthermore, the combination of a massive shortage of clinicians and the leading cause of death worldwide means a huge potential for disruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/goog.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although they made the headlines, the ugly underbelly of this technology is dependent on agile and interoperable hospital systems–both of which have made tremendous progress over the past decade (&lt;a href=&quot;https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/blog/2013/05/24/more-half-doctors-now-use-electronic-health-records-thanks-administration-policies&quot;&gt;Thanks, Obama&lt;/a&gt;). Google has deep learning experts and world renowned scientists, but at the end of the day any team’s ability is a function of data quality and quantity. Open source, clean, and anonymized medical records are critical. We have a long way to go until CSV heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, with new machine learning applications coming right and left when are we actually going to start trusting these things? Obviously, this method needs to be thoroughly validated before it can be used in a clinical setting, but when is “good” good enough? The traditional &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HeartScore&quot;&gt;Systematic COronary Risk Evaluation&lt;/a&gt; or “SCORE” method of predicting risk is correct 72% of the time, while Google’s was correct 70% of the time. How much strategic risk are health care organizations willing to take on for innovative technologies or increased productivity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sure as hell don’t have the answers, but the first step is asking the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="healthcare" /><category term="hype" /><summary type="html">Earlier this month Verily came out with an interesting piece of software that identifies several covariates with surprising accuracy from retinal scans of 300,000 patients. These features are fed into a model which yields the probability of suffering a major cardiac event. Although we’ve seen several versions of medical algorithms that aim to supplement or (gasp) replace physicians, this tech is unique in that it’s trying to repurpose existing data. Furthermore, the combination of a massive shortage of clinicians and the leading cause of death worldwide means a huge potential for disruption.</summary></entry></feed>